<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynnyth a traetys callyde the Lordis flayle handlyde by the bushops powre thresshere Thomas Solme</title>
            <author>Some, Thomas, b. ca. 1510.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1540</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105011</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840741</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840741</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5270</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5270)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 153:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynnyth a traetys callyde the Lordis flayle handlyde by the bushops powre thresshere Thomas Solme</title>
                  <author>Some, Thomas, b. ca. 1510.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By me Theophyll Emlos, vndere the sygne of sente Peters kay [i.e. widow of C. Ruremund,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printyde at Basyl [i.e. Antwerp] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1540?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The imprint in the colophon is false; actual place of publication, printer's name, and suggested publication date from STC. The printer's name is the author's name spelled backwards (STC).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ten Commandments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5270:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5270:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyth a traetys cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyde the Lordis flayle hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyde by the Buſhops powre threſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Thomas Solme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5270:2"/>
            <p>GOod redere here thow haſte a ſhorte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis callyd the lordis flaylle whych ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> dreue the to the confeſchione of one Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and ſauyure the ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de perſone yn trynyte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; mane / Whych flayll is handlyde by the hops powre threſſhere Thomas ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne / a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> theyre correccion I ſubmytie my ſelffe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> wrytte ony thynge contrary to te truthe / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this I ſett forte a worke of iuſtificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yn I wyll declare the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis of Chry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Sacramentis ynſtitute of the Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> pwrely &amp; ſyncerely as ſcripture do teſtify a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to the declaracyone of the beſte cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Wherfor pray to the Lorde for me and all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re laborynge yn the lordis vynarde to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of hys name / &amp; worthily acceptet hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> powre worke / the fyrſte taſte that I fynde yn the lordis ſwett<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / whych taſte I pray God ſende all yng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norante per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5270:2"/>
            <head>¶ A forme howe we ſhal know God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He effecte of holy ſcripture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtyth chefly yn two partis / That is. In knowlege of God &amp; owre ſelues. We ſhall kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we God fowre mannere of ways. Fyrſt yf we pryntyt yn owre hertes by a certen fayth / God to be ynfynitte wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bdam / rightwyſnes / goodnes / verite / vertw and lyffe / &amp; wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuere thes vertws er ſene or don yn ony place / to be only of hym / and of none othere / as all myracles / and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyons of mene and of al thynges that is good. We muſt only aſcrybe to God and to no ſaynte / othere yn heuen or erthe / as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do. ygnora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly for lake of thys knowlege.<note place="margin">Baruch. <hi>3.</hi> Iacob. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecunde way to knouwe God / is to beleue all thyngis.<note place="margin">Prouer. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Pſal. <hi>148.</hi> Danie. <hi>3.</hi> Roma. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Whych er yn heuyne and yn erthe / to be creatyde yn hys glory / &amp; that eche creature owghte to ſerue hym by ryght. by the reſon of theyr creacion / and nature / alſo they muſt ynſpecte hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment / obay hys mayeſte / and knowlege hym yn obayunge / to be theyere lorde and kynge.</p>
            <p>Thurdly we muſt confeſſe hym to be a ryghtuſe youge / and therfore ſhall reuenge<note place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>7.</hi> Roma. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:3"/>ſtrayghtly in them which declyne from his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis / Which do nott obay his will by all thingis / which ſhall thinke / ſpecke / or do ony thinge elſe then thos which pertayne to his glory / and honore.<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Forthly we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydere / that he is mercyfull and meke / and to reſayue mercy fully ſynneres &amp; wreches
/ which do drawe to his mercy / and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de his fayth / always redy to forgeue if ony do are forgeneſſe / to ſuckure if ony do inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſeyre his helpe / to ſaue if ony wyl retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and fyre theyre holl truſt in him.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>103.</hi> Ieſa. <hi>55.</hi> Pſalm. <hi>25</hi> &amp;. <hi>85.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ A forme to knowe owre ſelues.</head>
            <p>WE ſhall knowe owre one perſons thus / We owght to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydere owr fyrſte fathere Adam / to be created to the ymage and ſimylitude of God / that is in wyſdam / rightwyſnes / indude wyth holy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / &amp; ſo cleuynge to God by thes geftis of grace / ſhulde euere lyue in him / if he had per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeuerid &amp; ſtande ſuerly in this clernes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / which he toke of God. But after he was corrupte in ſynne / this ymage and ſimy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litude of God was ſeducte &amp; blottyd.<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte all goodnes of godly grace / by which he<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:3"/>might aperſeueryd (if he hade willyd) in the way of trute / and lyffe. By ſyne he is deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyd fare from God &amp; made a nothere mane / robbyd and ſpowilide of all wyſſdam / right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſnes / vertwe &amp; lyffe / Which he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne not haue but only of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 5.</note> Wherfore nothynge elſe is lefte to man / but ygnorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / iniquite / wekenes / dethe / and yougmente / which aer the fruttis of ſynne / Which calamyte did not fal only in him but is ſhede alſo in them that cum of his ſeede / Therfor all men which er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>borne of Adam terreſtrial / aer ygnoraunte &amp; voyd of God / peruers / corrupte / &amp; deſtitute of all goodnes / Owre thowght worde and ded euer a genſte godis wyll / although we ſhowe ſum goodnes in forme / neuertheleſſe theſame inwerde affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the mende aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith in his fylthynes / and blynde peruerſite / The yougmente of whiche mende or herte / partayn only to God / which letyll regarde the owght werde ſhynynge / but only be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the ſecretes of the herte.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.</note> Therfor lett a man haue of him ſelffe neuer ſo bowtyfull a face conſernyng holynes / it is nothinge els but hypocriſy / and before God alſo abomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion / by cauſe lyuynge infleſſe peruers co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gitacions of mynde and corruptible deſeyrs be euer in man.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 16. <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5270:4"/>
            <p>ALthowgh truly we be ſo borne / that there is nothinge lefte in vs to do ony thinge which is accepte or cane be to God / nor is not lefte in owre vertwe to pacyfy or to make acceptable to him
/ neuer the leſſe / we do not ſeſſe to be detters in that thinge / which we cane not geue
/ or reſtore / In as muche we be the creaturs of God / &amp; he beyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge all mighty do not ſeſſe to creat / and conſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vs moſt wrechyd &amp; ſynfull / therfor er we euer bownde to ſerue his honor and glory in knowlegyng his goodnes / and owr one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmyte in obſeruyge his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundmentes. Nor it is not lawful to pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>etde an excuſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / by cauſe faculte or abilyte is abſente or lake / and as waſt full detters which aer not abyll to pay. Truly it is owre fawt &amp; ſynne which hold vs bownde that we can nethere wyll or may do good.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8. <hi>Roma.</hi> 7.</note> But whan God is the youſie reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gere of ſyns / it be houythe that we kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welege owre ſelues worthy maledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; to deſerue yougmente of eternall dethe. Truly there is no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyllith / or may do thos thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gis which partayne to owre offece / duty or iuſtificacion. Wherfor in ſcripture we er cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd the childrene of yre / and condempnacion and youge vs all hedlyngis in to dethe and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Roma.</hi> 3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:4"/>perdicion / Therfore there is nothinge lefte to man / wherin he ſhuld ſeeke his rightwyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / vertw / lyff / &amp; helth in him ſelffe / which all thingis aer but in one God
/ from whom man ſett a parte &amp; deuidide / before him ſelffe ſhall not fynde / but infelicite / vnabilite / ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite / deth / and the ſame hells / that is / the vttermoſte malediction for ſynne / which is the returninge in to erthe / and in to the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyuſnes of godes bliſſyngis and geftis.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſee.</hi> 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>LEft man ſhuld be ygnorante of thes thyngis / the lorde dyd geue / and in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nere prynte in the hertis of all men a lawe / which is callyd the lawe of nature / This la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we truly is no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> othere thynge thene mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſchyens / or for knowlege / which is inwerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a recorde to vs of thos thyngis which we owe dwely to God / and do ſhowe vs that which is good and yll / and therfore ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and hold vs gilty / whils we er knowne to owre ſelues / not to be (as we owght) of abilite to make ſatiſfaccion for owre offencis and myſdedes / that is by owre workis can neuere ſatiſfy or purches agen the rightwyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / vertw / and lyffe / which aer loſte by owr one freewyll.<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>2.</hi> The cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall lawe.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5270:5"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The cauſe of the lawe of Moyſes</note> ANd by cauſe man after werdes was &amp; is ſwolne by arrogaunce &amp; pryde / and ſo blyndide by his one loue / that he can not be holde his one ſelffe / and deſcende in him ſelffe / and to knowlege his one wrechidnes and myſery / the lorde dyd put to vs a lawe writtyn / by which we er leruyd of the parfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie rightwyſnes which the lorde require / and what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nere a rightwyſnes it is / and howe we ſhall fulfyl it / and that is if we fyxe owr ſelues growndly and holly in God / &amp; whan in all thingis that we thinke / deſeyre / ſpeke or do we intende and ſquare it to his honore and glory. And this lawe writtine do ſhowe to vs howe fare we be abſente from the right way. And for this caus / all promiſſis &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lediccions er putt in the ſame lawe / there tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the lorde do promiſſe / if ony ſhall fulfyll it perfectly &amp; eractly by word &amp; dede / what ſo euer he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / that he wyll geue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of eternal helth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18.</note> Wherby he ſhowe the ſame ꝑfectnes of lyffe to be the very right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſnes / which is towght in the lawe / &amp; ſo to be hade before him / and that this parfection of lyffe were worthy ſuche a rewarde / if by ony mens it might befownde a monge men.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.</note> Agen he promiſſe malediction in all men / 
<pb facs="tcp:5270:5"/>and pronowſyth an eternal iougment of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the / which do not obſerue plentyuſly &amp; with owt ony exception the hole rightwyſnes / of the lawe / the which payn / malediction / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do beynde and ſubdue all men truly which euer hathe byne / is / or ſhalbe / to confeſſe them ſelues ſynneres and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſers of the lawe / and thes thingis truly we know by the lawe of Gode.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 1.</note> Wherfore the lawe whyls it do ſhowe and teche vs the wyll of God the which wil to be fulfyllyd we er bowde / and whylis it ſhowe that we do very lytyll of thos thingis / which we aer bownde to do pwrly and ſyncerly / it is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſpectacle to vs in which we may ſe the goodneſſe of God and beholde wyſtly owre ſynne / and malediction as in a claſſe of ſtele we be holde the fyllthynes &amp; ſpottis of owre mouth / And this lawe is nothinge but the teſtimony of the naturall lawe which ſtere and moue ofte tymys owre memory inwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly / whos moniſchio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nowe by te lawe writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn is incowlkyd and dreuyne into owr her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis / which before we dyd not kype faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whene the lawe of nature dyd teche vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werdly.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Nowe it is redy to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de what we ought to lerne of the lawe / truly God to
<pb facs="tcp:5270:6"/>be owre creatore / almighty / lord and fathere. wherfore we owgt to geue him all dwe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor / glory and loue. Alſo ye muſt notte / by cauſe we be all the chyldren of yre / therfor as conſeruynge owre ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fulnes / to be all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy malediction / iougme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / ye at the laſt eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall dethe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Whan we haue thus lernid owr one infirmyte then we muſte not diſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vtterlly / but ſeke remidy by his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty / &amp; note by workis / &amp; ſo he is redy to helpe for Chriſtis ſak which is his only marcy and remiſſion of ſynne.</head>
            <p>THerfore if we wylle optayn helth it ys to by ſowght ſum othere ways then be the rightwyſnes of workis / which helt is remiſſion of ſynne. Furthermore whan it is not in owre ſelues / that is / in owr vertw and faculte to pay that we owe to the lawe / we owt to diſpayrs in owronſelues / &amp; to are &amp; lokefore helpe ſum othere whare.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iacob.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Petri.</hi> 5.</note> And whan we thus humbyll and meke owre ſelues in knowleginge owr one infirmyte and wekeneſſe / then the lorde do a pere to vs / and exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him ſelffe aeſy / me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / and forgeuinge / of whom it is wrytten / 
<pb facs="tcp:5270:6"/>that he reſiſtyth prowde men / and geue gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to meke. If we deſeyre fyrſt his yre wyth faythfullnes / &amp; axe forgeueneſſe / wyth owt dowght he do remitt his yre to vs / what ſo mener owre ſynnes dyd deſerue he remytt &amp; take vs in grace / by whos grace we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayue a owe herte / by which we wyll / and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>we vertw by which we may execute his vertws.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 3.</note> And all this truly he largly imparte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſtribute vnto vs / for Ieſu Chriſt / owre lorde / Which whan he was on God wyth te fathere / he dyd do on owre fleſh / wharby he myght begyn a cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te with vs / and drawe vs nere to God / from whom owre ſyns dyd make vs fare diſtaunte.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ieſa.</hi> 53. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.</note> Which by meryth of his dethe dyd pay owre dettis to the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſenes of God / and pacifyde his yre
/ rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ynge vs from malediction and yougmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> / to which we wore bownde / and bore the payne of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his body that we myght be abſoylyd by theſam. He deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyd from heuen and brought with him all plentuuſnes of he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynly bliſſyngis / which he ſhede in vs by a large hande / in ſendynge his holy gooſt / by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we er regenerate / &amp; deliueryde from the nowre &amp; ſnaris of the deuell / we ere optay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yd by godly grace ynto the children of God<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iod.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 7 <hi>Roma.</hi> 8.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:7"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:7"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:8"/>and er ſanctifyde to euery good worlte by whom alſo howe longe we aer in this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall body / all peruers couyttuſues / fleſſly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeyrs and what elſe ſo euer / the crokyd / and corrupte peruerſyte of nature do generate aer mortifide in vs / by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from day to day we ere regenerate / that we myght walke in nouite of lyffe / and lyue to rightwyſnes. All thes thingis eroffryd and geuen in Chryſt owre lorde / truly remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynne / by grace only / pece &amp; reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyliacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with god / the geftis of the holy goſte / if we do amplecte and take them by a certen fayth / and therby cleue to the goodnes of God / and as men reſtynge and nothynge doughtinge / but that the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of God is veryte and truth / which do pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſeſe to vs all thos thingis / &amp; thus yowyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyde to him do poſſeſſe all heuenly blyſſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis / treſurs / and geſtis gooſtly / which ſhall lede vs in to lyffe and helth
/ which we ſhall neuer optayn but by a lyuely &amp; a true fayth whyllis we confeſſe all owre goodnes to be in him / we truly to be nothynge but in him / and for certente we muſt aſucre / &amp; promyſſe to owre ſelues / in him to be made the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God / and partakers of the kyngdam of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1. <hi>Roma.</hi> 8.</note> Agen they which haue not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb facs="tcp:5270:8"/>in Chriſte / of what degre ſo euer they be / what ſo meuer they do or go a bought
/ is to theyre perdicion and confuſion / and iou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gment of eternall deth abiecte from God / &amp; excludyd from the acceptacion of all helth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Iou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this cognyſchio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of owre ſelues (by which we er tought to humbyll &amp; caſte downde owre ſelues before God a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to ſeke his marcy / alſo this ſayth which geue vs the taſte of the godli goodnes / &amp; mercy / bi which he worket wyth vs in his Chryſt) is not of vs / or put in owre faculte / god is to be prayd that he do bringe vs by a trwe repentaunce / in theſame knowlege of owre ſelues / &amp; with a ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te fayth in this knowlege of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfulneſſe / and ſwettnes / which he ſhowe in his Chriſte / that he beynge gyde / we may be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e vnto the eternall beatitude / which chriſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the vnical way / wherby we cum to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And that men which ere ſymple may the better knowe the cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myunge in to this way of truth / we ſhall declare the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis of the lawe / which (as I ſhowde befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re) do dreue vs to Chryſt / in knowlegynge the goodnes of God and owre one naught<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynes / and hewe all grace / marcy / &amp; remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynne is only optaynyd by a ſuerfayth in Chriſtis blude.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5270:9"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynnyth the tenne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundmentis.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here aer ten preceptis of the lawe / fowre partayn to Godis honore / &amp;. vi. to the loue of owre nayghbore / Wherfore the Lorde (as the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelyſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyth) dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude brefly the laue in two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis / That we ſhuld loue God with all owr hertis / all owre mendes / and all owre ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth / owre nayghbore as owre ſelues / But althowgh the vnyuerſall lawe is concludyd in thos too chappiters / neuer the leſſe owre Lorde wherby he myght take a way the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excuſacion / it pleſyd him to ſhowe more largly &amp; playnly by ten preceptis both thos thyngis which partayne to his honore fare / and loue / as thoſe whych he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand vs for his ſake to bere to owre nayghbores.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 32. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.</note> The fyrſt is this.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10</note>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="commandment">
               <head>¶ The fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment.</head>
               <head type="sub">Thow ſhalt not haue ſtraunge Godis before me.</head>
               <p>BY which we ere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyde to haue a ſtedfaſte fayth / and tho ſeke all ways remydy of him that we do not geue the lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of ony goodnes and vertw / to a nothere<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ieſa.</hi> 30. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 31. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>Deute.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 10.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:9"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reature / which belongyth only to hym / It be houe vs alſo to loue and fere him a boue all thyng / that we knowledge hym only for owre God / fyxynge all owre hope and truſt in hym / thynkynge what ſo euer goodnes chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe to vs to be of him / admittynge at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ony thinge but that in which he is wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppyd / &amp; honoryde.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10</note> Nor we owt not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare him thus by tonge
/ geſture of body &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y euery owtworde ſingnyficacion / that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be owre God / but alſo we muſt geue owr ſelffe lyke by mende / herte &amp; all owre ſtody.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 28</note> For not only owr wordis &amp; externall dedes aer before him / but alſo the workis of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe herte &amp; cogitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the inwerde mende / er mor better &amp; clerely opinyde to him thene owre ſelues. And ye ſhall not that ther was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euer
/ is / or ſhalbe ony man (Chriſte ony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cepte which is bothe God and man) that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er fulfillyd this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te / which lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we God with all his mynd / herte and ſowle. Nottywtſtandynge he do geue vs this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment vnpoſſibyl for vs to fulfyll in this mortall body / by cauſe he wold dreue vs to Chriſte / that is (as I tolde you before) to confeſſe owre one infirmyte / and remiſſion of ſynne to be had only by his marcy &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.
<pb facs="tcp:5270:10"/>This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment teche vs whylis we walke in this corrupte fleſſe that we er not ꝑfeyt / &amp; willyth that we ſtreche owre ſelues forwerdis to the marke and gole by a true fayth / where we ſhall reſayue all parfectues / and ſe God face to face / owre ſauyore Chriſt Ieſu beynge owre mene and gyde. This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtope the mowghte of boſters &amp; crakers reioyſyng in workis / and dreue all men to ſeke owre ſauyre Chriſt Ieſu.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te we er forby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyne to prefere ony worldly goodis or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocions / as rycheſe / honor / dingnyte &amp; ſych othere aboue God / we may not ſett owre mend ſo on them that we ſhal forgytte God. But froz tyme to tyme we muſt euer know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege him / as is ſayd before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="commandment">
               <head>¶ The ſecund co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment.</head>
               <head type="sub">Thow ſhall make no grauene y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage / or ſimilytude of thos thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gis whych aer aboue in heuyne or in erthe benethe / or in waters which ere vnder the erthe / thow ſhalte not honore ne worſhope them.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>BY which is ſyngnifyde all honore and worſhope to be lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to on God / which whan he can not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyd by nomens of mans capacyte or wytt / in as mych he is incorporall inuyſyble / ſo ſpirytall that he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne be excludyde from no place / lett not vs flowmbere that we can comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de him by owre one wyttis and ymaginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.10. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 4.</note> Nor lett not vs worſhope an ydol<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as it were the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lytude of God which is a ſpryte / and wylbe worſhippyd in ſpryte and truth. Therfor the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement do ſhowe one Gode to be / be ſyde whom ther is non othere God to be thougt or hade. This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundmente do teche what maner a God he is / and by what kynde or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of worſhype he wylbe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noryde / leſt we ſhuldebe bolde to fayne ony carnall thynge lyke to hym / or to caſte hym vnder owre wyttis &amp; braynes / or to be repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hendyde by ony forme / or ſymilytude.</p>
               <p>A ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt ydolis of the trinyte &amp; ſayntes.</p>
               <p>LLett them reſpecte hethere which inten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to defende by a miſerabyll prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecrabyll ydolitre / by which meny yers be for this tyme / true relygion haue bynue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne / and ſubmerſyde. They ſay ymagis aer not reputyd as Godis. Nor the Iuys
<pb facs="tcp:5270:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>were not ſo obliuyus but that they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryd God to be / by woſe hand they were le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de owt of Egypte / befor they made the claf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe. Nor Turkis er not to be though ſo dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyttyd / but that they do beleue God to be a nothere thynge then ſtone &amp; wodde. They do chonge allways ymagys after theyre on fancy / but they hold all ways in mend theyre God / and dedycatt meny ydolis in the name of on falſe God / but do not beleue to haue ſo meny Godis / as they haue ydolis / Alſo they do make uwe euery day / but they do not thynke to make nwe Godis. What nowe? All ydolyters of Iuys or gentelis / had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue God to be ſuch a wone as the vanyte of theyre brayn dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayue. Therfor the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de dyd generate an ydolle / &amp; a hand brought it forthe / neuertheleſſe the Iuys dyd thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke them ſelues to worſhope vnder ſuch yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gys God eternall / on and very Lorde in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and erthe / Alſo gentyls dyd ſo repute theyre godis (altough fallis) which alſo they fayned to be in heuene. To this they dyd not beleue God to be preſente to them / excepte they dyd ſhowe hym by a carnall preſence / And that they myght obay this blind deſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / they dyd erecte ſignys / &amp; ydolis / by which
<pb facs="tcp:5270:11"/>they dyd beleue to haue God preſente be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for theyr corporall eyes / Whan truly they though them ſelues to be hold God in them / then they worſhoppyd him in them. And ſo beholdyng ydolis wyth mende and eyes as meny chriſtyans do noweadays / they bege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to be more beſtly then holy / inthinkynge holy that which is a ydoll. He that wyl de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this to be done before owre days and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo nowe he denyth the truth onſhamfaſtly. Why do they ly proſtrate before them: Why do they turne themſelues to them intendyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to pray as to the aerys of God: Why aer they redy for ſuch popyttis and ydollis to ſtryues / debatis / brawlyngis and chyding is as gentels be for theyr ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myttis? Meny nowe a days wylſoffere more wyllynge on God to be takyne a way then theyr ydolis &amp; poppetis hauynge beſydis thys meny othe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re groſſe accors wyth owt nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bere / by which God grettly is dyſpleſyd / but ſhulbe grettly pleſyde if they purifyde themſelues / from ydolytre and ſuch yllis. They ſay we do not call them Godis / no more dyd the Iuys or gentyls call them but only ſingnys and yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gis of Godis.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ieſa.</hi> 40. <hi>Iere.</hi> 2. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 6.</note> And truly all prophetis and holy ſcripture do not ſelfe to forbyd fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:5270:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>wyth wode and ſton / where all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyans (which er the true Iuys) er in excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byll as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernynge the carnall worſhyppyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of God in wode and ſtone / or ony othere erthely thynge.<note place="margin">Haba. <hi>2.</hi> Deut. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> And ye ſhall not that the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſte effuge &amp; ſcape that all papiſtis haue to vpholde theyre ydolis / is to affirme them the bokis of ydiotis and lay man. And that we grante this (although it be a thinge moſt folyſh and vayn whan they er ſett vpe wyth owt dowte for non othere cauſe then to be worſhypyde) hyt neuer the leſſe I can not ſe what fcuttis they brynge to ydiotis and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lernyd perſons / chefly when God is caruyd to them / but to make them heritykes in bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge to haue God preſent all hole by men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers / as they carue &amp; paynte him.<note place="margin">The car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of God ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke herety kis. The car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of fayntis make bawdis.</note> And ſuch ymagis as preſente fayntis / what er they but examples of grett ſuperfluyte / coſtloſte and a tityll of an yll name: Fore harlottis do ſhowe more ſhamfaſtly &amp; moderattly / theyr horly a ray and owtwerd oſtencions / then tempils do theyr picturs which they wyll to repreſente the ymagis of virgyns. Therfore lett them decke theyre ymagis att the leſt ways / with ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhamfaſtnes / that they might repreſente ſum what mor ſhamfaſtly to be
<pb facs="tcp:5270:12"/>bokis of ſum holynes. As they be mad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we a days / they ſhal prouoke a man mor to ſyne them vertwe. But as towchynge they re opynion ymagis to be bokis of ydiotis is not the way and reſon to teche the pepell of God / whom God wyll to be inſtructe by a nothere techynge &amp; by a nothere boke / then by the bockis of blockis and ſtokis and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh lyes / and fabyllis.<note place="margin">To make ymagis bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kis is nott the true w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay teche y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diottis.</note> He hath ſhowde the prechynge of hys worde to be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn to all men / to be a bocke whych ſhall te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vs only the way of truthe. Therfor to what ende do it perteyn to ſett vp ſo meny croſſis of wode / ſton / if that thynge be oft ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes betynne in owre aeris / Chriſt to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayd for owre ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / &amp; that he ſofferyd owre malediction a pon the cros / and dyd waſh a way owre ſyns / of which on worde they may lerne more then of a thowſante croſſis of wode or ſtonne / much leſſe then nede croſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſis of gold and ſyluer / which ſhall make a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyttus mend more to remenber Mammon then Chriſte.<note place="margin">Not the gret ydolie of the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de.</note> Othere Idolis there be in the worlde which er mor grette mor abomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byll then thes forſayd / which aſcende into the trone of God / and boſte themſelues to be lyke the all mighty. Agenſt which who ſo
<pb facs="tcp:5270:13"/>ſpecke the ypocritys and popyſche ſorte ſe them condempnyd to deth / which euer haue byne a geuſte Gode / both in old and nowe Teſtament in ſleynge profyttis &amp; true diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyls which ſpake the true worde of God / in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendyng to plucke downe them wyth theyr ydolis reſtynge in godis place / as men vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly intendyng to expulſſe God / ye and theyre maleſſe was ſo grett that they dyd not ſpare the ſonne of God / whom the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall yugis wold haue deliueryd.<note place="margin">Truth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruith eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re hath.</note> Wherfore though in ſpekinge the trothe deth muſt nedis folowe by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis of thes blowde ſuckers / hyt the truth muſt be prechede yet Chriſt muſt be extollyd of them that knowythe the truthe / For he that deny him (as he wyttnes him ſelffe) before men / he wyll deny him before his heuenly fathere
/ Wherfore cheryte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellyth ☞ me to tell truthe as conſernynge ydo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lis contrary to this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment. And ye ſhall not that a monge all ydollis whiche er in this worlde wyth tryumphe in the ſette &amp; tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue of God allmighty. that is / which reſte by a falſſe fayth in the herte of man which herte is the ſett of God / is popyſche preſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / and his grett Gode / For popyſche preſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de what by hypocriſy / and by the falſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence<note place="margin">The ydoll of preſtode popyſch.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:13"/>of maſterſhyue which he holde vnder theyre veno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mus Gode / hath ſo infecte by theyr deſaytfull promyſſis / the hertis of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyll / that whare Chriſt was wonte to rayne with his ſwett promyſſis / by theyre poppy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres they haue clerely erpulſyd him / and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollyde Antychriſte with his marchantis ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonicalle / And whan preſtode popyſche with his falſſe god thus ſupplyth the place of God / what er they but ydollis: ye and ſo meny as beleue to be ydolaters: Lett vs ſherch what an ydolle is and we ſhall fynde the thinge clerly verifyde of them.<note place="margin">The defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſchion of an ydole.</note> An ydoll truly is nothyng in the thingis of nature / that is / altowgh it expreſſe ony thinge as all ydollis do. othere God / angell / ſaynth / deuel / ſonne / mon / beſte or ſuch / lyke / it ere they but ydollis. And why: by cauſe they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue noparte of the ſubſtaunce and properte. Not with ſtanding hyt an ydolle is ſo playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly expreſte by colore &amp; byce / that a folle ſhall reſpecte it as the thynge / and hyt it haue no properte of the naturall thynge. This conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deringe what ydolle ſhall you fynde mor leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe repreſentynge the ſubſtaunce / more myſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge the properte of nature then popyſche preſtode? They clayme the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God
<pb facs="tcp:5270:14"/>that is to make Chriſte / and to remytt ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / and it in all properies they er lyke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. And this falſe ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / this theyre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtabyll ydoll of popyſche preſtoude / is ſo craftyly payntyd / and ſett owt by blaſynge colors / that excepte a man haue lyght of the ſonne of rightwyſnes / he ſhall neuer diſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne theverite from falſhed
/ the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from the ydoll / Ther is no payntere ſo cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge in laynge his colers a pone an ydoll / as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychriſt is inſettinge owt of his this ydoll of popyſche preſtode / The growne colers that he vſe be thes / oyſter gatherers / I wold ſay Oſtiares / whos offyce is to pute the kay in the dors. and dreue doggis owt of the cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / lectores / that is reders of leſons / Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſte / cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerers of watter ſallte / Acoluti / apyk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker of ſalettis
/ Subdiaconus / a pyſtell in arre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / Diaconꝰ / a goſpell gloſere.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. boke of ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en. diſt. 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 9.</note> And then the cheffyſt colore of all
/ Sacerdos / a makere &amp; geuere of Godis fleſſe and bonys / ſeuene co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers he vſe fore the .vii. geſtis of the holy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte. Not withſtandynge ſum be not contente with thes colers
/ but they adde to more on be fore and a nothere be hynde / that is / Ton<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurati. he that is clypte or ſhorne in the crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / and Epiſcopi / he that ſlepe ouer his flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / 
<pb facs="tcp:5270:14"/>with meny othere debattis which payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this ydoll haue as I ſhall ſhowe here after in his proper place if God grant mely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe. Meny othere colers they haue wherby they ſett forte this theyr preſtod / as amyſſis albys / fanellis / ſtollis / &amp; the veſtime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which couere the multitude of ſynne / &amp; ſuche othe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / wherby they tranſmutte themſelues in to an angell of lighte and wyl aſcende in to the hy trone and be lyke to the allmighty. But although theyre nawghtty and rottyne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce be thuſe ſett owt by colers
/ and be made as a God / hyt is it but an ydoll / lakin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the thinge and the propertys of the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / not hauynge the vertwe of God in remit tynge ſynne / and in geuynge lyffe. For we haue but on God whom we owt to fere and honore with all owre hert / mend and ſowle as was ſayd before. And a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne by cauſe all men do declyne from righwyſues / and there is non that do good but only owre Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſte. Agen by cauſe all men a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re lyers euery man is a curſt which truſte in men. Nowe in aſmiche popiſchyreſtode do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe themſelues ſpiritall and all goſtly / ſauyers and makkers of Godis / ye and very vicarys of Gode / therfor we muſt nedis conclude / 
<pb facs="tcp:5270:15"/>that they er but ydollis payntyd of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt / by cauſe they lake the ſubſtaunce of all godly vertws / whos perſon they clayme by thayre payntyd ydoll of popyſch preſtode. This thinge herde perchance ſum man wyll ſay / I maruyll then that owre buſhops wold ſo playnly and purly wright of this ordere of preſtode / ſettynge forte ſo euery order with a ſage grauyte / in as mych owre ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme hede dyd commaunde them to ſhowe that thynge which myght be to the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore of God &amp; profyth of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muns. Lett no mane meruyll thowgh they haue a ſnake of theyr onwyll / that is thowgh they reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte theyre one profyte and glory and mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne ſum what popyſchues / which thowgh it be nothynge fore profyte it is it good fore paſtyme.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Reg. 10</note> In as mych it is all cungerynge &amp; lurgeredemayne / Which thinge is prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd I thynke verily in the olde teſtamente / where mencion is made that Salomone dyd ſend his ſhyps one in thre yers / in to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſys / which brought gold and ſyluer / and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantis tethe / and apes / &amp; pecokis / So owre kynge Henry the .viij. whos byfe I pray god to kepe / which is a very Salomon / what is / which is paciente &amp; quiette in conſchens / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifyenge
<pb facs="tcp:5270:15"/>hyme ſelfe and his accordynge to Godis worde / which is the lyf of the fowlle / he by his nobyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell / hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyde his buſhops and docters / to lede his ſhyps in to Tharſys and to brynge of the beſte / fruttis &amp; treſurs / that is to lede his cherche of which he is ſuppreme hede imediattly after Chriſt / into the contemplacion of Godis promyſſis in the ſherchynge of owr ſtony hertis / which is ſignifyd by Tharſis / Tharſis whas ſuch a pleſaunte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre and ſo ryche / that is was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd the contemplacion of yoy / And what is mor yoy ful to behold / then the ſwette promiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſys of Chriſtis blude?<note place="margin">Tharſy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> In to this laude owre buſhops and prechers were ſente to veche of the beſte treſure and ryches / And they haue browte parte after his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment / parte after theyr on fancy and brayns. After his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement they haue brought gold and ſyluer / that is / in ſum thynge they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe theyre cherches wyth the true workis of faythe / with the pure worde of god which as the profyt ſayth is a chaſte and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defylyd ſpeche / gold and ſyluer prouyd by fyre. And after theyre mendis they haue brought elephantis tethe / to make trones &amp; reſting placis / that is / they vpholde theyr on
<pb facs="tcp:5270:16"/>glory and dignyte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maintyne falſſe ſectis of antichriſtis angellis / the pwyſone ordere of popyſche preſtode / which dewouere the goodis of fatherleſſe &amp; motherleſſe chyldren / Which ſectis alſo is ſignifyde by the apes / which er beſtis of mockege / and lawghynge more then for profyt or helpe / which ſhalbe garniſchyd with a cott and bere the ſimilitud of men and yt er but ydolis and apys as towchych the propertis of man / which cane not ſpecke but moke and mowe / as owre po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſche ſorte do in all theyre actis and dydis
/ clayminge the ſimilitude and ſubſtaunce of Gode / and in dedis er but apes / that is a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge ſtoke to owre Salomon and his true ſubiectis.<note place="margin">Antichriſte a his flocke er dewoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rera. Popyſhnes is but apy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhnes.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Popyſhers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eyoys in theyre tayll as the peco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke.</note> Which ſectis alſo is ſignifid by the pecokes / whos pride is in theyre tayll / that is in the blynde ſorte of onlernyd pepyll / which hange to theme and truſt to theyre po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſch ſeremonys / which reyoyce in theyre workis and operacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and extoll themſelues as the ſpectacle or onperleſſe flowere of this worlde / which pekokis more reyoyce in theyre taylle
/ that is / in theyr workis &amp; blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de folowers / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in theyr hede / &amp; ſauyure Chriſt Ieſwe. Therfor I pray God for the merytis of Chriſtis blude brynge this grett
<pb facs="tcp:5270:16"/>ydoll downe wytt al his gynnes and proper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / and ſend him a ſcorynge of his colers / that his ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce may a pere as it is in ded / which in ded is but fylthy / ſynfull &amp; of no va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lure. ¶ Such thinges as Chriſt dyd vſe ande inſtitute to his grett glory / and owr profyth goſtly. thos haue the Pope and his menbres chongyd to his grett dyſhonore / and owre damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for he ſent them as miniſters / but they make them ſelues ſauyers / gloryfinge themſelues to make the ſecunde perſon in trinyte / whom the fathere of heuene culd ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer make but of him ſelf generat by whom he is with owt beginnyng or endynge.<note place="margin">Of theyre maſſe God.</note> By the reſon of the which grett ydolytre ye the moſt gretyſt that can be is don ygnorauntly &amp; for lake of knowlege of meny. In as mych the pepyll ſett theyre holle affiaunce &amp; truſte in that God / hauynge nothynge ſo much in theyre herte / as that God / liuynge or lyenge a departynge by dethe / they chefly call for ſere Ihon &amp; his God / thinkynge as they er towght that wyth owt them God haue no powre to ſaue them / excepte as they ſay it be in neceſſyte / then they ſay and grante God may worke with owt them / but then you muſt take hyd / for ſo God can not do ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there
<pb facs="tcp:5270:17"/>excepte you haue a wyll to haue S. Ihon and his God / if it wore poſſyble / Ho ſhame / Thus by thys mens they rauyſche the hertes of all men and plucke them clene from God eternall and fyxe them in theyre workis and falſſe God / affirmyng that thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge which Chriſt dyd inſtitute in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to be a thinge in ded of the ſame fleſſe and blude borne of the virgyne Mary / and that to be done in ſaynge thos wordes. This tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly is / my body / Agen.<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>27.</hi> The wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die makyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge.</note> This is my blude of the nwe teſtament / which ſhalbe ſhede for meny in remiſſion of ſynne / which wordis ſpokynne with on wynne ouer the bred and wynne / with a ſtynkinge brethe at the laſt ende they affirme to be and wyll make vs be leue the bred and wynne to be chongyd into the very fleſſe and blud of Chriſt. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue to blowe owt the holy goſte owt of the fathers boſome / and to brynge with him the holl body of Chriſt borne of the virgyn and to conſayue it a genne in the cake and wyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he dyd in the virgyns womme. This is theyr fayth if thes wordis be ſpokyn chefly with on brethe / but if they take two brethes then they er in dowte. And this they worſho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe as God and wyll vs alſo ſo to do / Hade
<pb facs="tcp:5270:17"/>Chriſt ſuch a beleu whan he ſpake thes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis? Dyd he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde his diſcipyls to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope it? Do not they teche alſo the contrary?<note place="margin">Chriſt dyd not ſo bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue nor teche And they ſynge the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary dayly in thy meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe crede / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d prime.</note> We rede in theyr maſſe crede / I beleue in on Lorde Ieſu Chriſt the ſone of God / only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gottyn and borne of the fathere before all workis / God of God / lyght of lyght / very God of very God be gottyn and not made / of ſubſtaunce euen lyke to the fathere / by whom all thyngis be made.<note place="margin">Chriſt is vndemade.</note> We rede alſo in the Pſalme of Nuicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vult / The fathere God / the ſon God / the holy goſt is God / Vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mad is the fathere / vnmade is the ſone / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mad is the holy goſte / Ar not thes wordis theyre on ſonge
/ O wylfull blyndnes / In as myth thes wordis betrue why duſte thow boſte and affirme to make God and Chriſt in fleſh and blude / with owt whom thow cau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſte not lyue / moue / or be.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> Nowe ſum wyl ſay / we make not Chriſte / it is the vertwe of his worde.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> We anſwere / If an infydell ſhuld ſpeke and blowe the wordis ouer the cake &amp; wynne / ſhuld the wordis chonge them into the very body and blud of Chriſte? I thynke they wold ſay nay / by cauſe they lake faythe. And who is faythfull / Non truly but he which truſt faythfully in the meritis of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtis
<pb facs="tcp:5270:18"/>blude / to inherytte heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly blyſſingis for Chriſtis ſake only / whos wyll is fyxid both day and nyght in the laue of owre lorde to fulfyll it ſpiritally in Chriſt. Them if he be faythfull which do beleue thus / It muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dys folowe that they er infydeles whiche do the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. And ſo they which haue not this beleue in Chriſt / but vpholde Antychriſt &amp; popyſchnes / truly they muſt nedys be infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels / and ſo nethere to make Chriſtis body in ſpekinge his wordis / or to ette him.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> And if this wyll not helpe / by cauſe they wyl ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a nothere cautell ſayng / as I haue herde f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yere preche bothe in Antuarpe and &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouen / that it is not the worde of Gode that make the body of Chriſtis fleſſe and blude / but the offiſe of Popyſch preſtod.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
                  </label>
                  <note place="margin">The inſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion of Chriſt.</note> The we anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue do more then Chriſt wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de do / Chriſt dyd inſtitute his ſupper. in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of his dethe / to be a ſygne and myſtery of his ſwett promiſſis / ſtabliſſhyd and fulfyllyd in his blude / whos ſygne / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce / and ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / is the brekynge of brede and ſhedynge of wynne annexyde to his wyl &amp; teſtimony of the ſame Chriſtis body &amp; blude onſe ſhede for owre redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on his proper autere / and now to be vſyd of<note place="margin">The breki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of bred / &amp; ſhedynge of wyne is a ſell anne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>xyde to the lordis teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:18"/>them that be faythfull (Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge (for remembraunce of this his deth paſte / wherby owre weke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſchience may be ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtyd &amp; ſtabliſſhyd in this fayth and promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis forſayd.<note place="margin">The vſe of the popiſch ſorte.</note> Popyſche preſtode do not vſe this ſacrament as a remembraunce but as a thynge renwede / and made a genne by they<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re wordis and bliſſyngis / and ſo whare the Iuys dyd crucify him ons / they lyke cruell tyrantis do crucify him dayly / and whare Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>das (confeſſinge his faute) for a lytyll lukere dyd be tray his blude / they vnrepentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te by cauſe they haue grett vantege wyll euer be ſellers / and trayters to Chriſtis blude. They ſay after the blowynge of theyre mouthe (as I ſayd before) the brede beynge brede is then chongyd and made the very body of Chriſte / really and ſubſtauncially. And then if he be there really (as they ſay) it is no thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of remembraunce no ſigne or ſacrament / but the ſelf ſubſtaunce / the ſelfe thyng.<note place="margin">The popi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſch Chriſte is Antichri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte.</note> But not well and with good cheryte / If they can make that thynge which is brede a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wynne / and ſhall peryſch and haue an ende / to be that thynge which is Chriſte &amp; euer ſhalbe with owt corrupcion / it muſt nedis folowe / this Chriſte mad of them in ſayng the forſayd
<pb facs="tcp:5270:19"/>wordis / to be Antichriſt and not the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of God / by cauſe he is dayly mad and dayly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſch as we may ſe be expedience. For lett them kepe theyre Chriſt longe informe of bred or wynne / &amp; theyre God theyre Chriſt ſhal ſtater full of wormes and ſtynke / nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not helpe him ſelffe / are / or haue helpe of his makers and cungerers / but by the dayly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wouerynge of teth &amp; bely.<note place="margin">Owre Chriſt is the ſone of Gode.</note> But owre chriſte in whos remembraunce we breke the brede and dryncke the wynne / dede neuer ſee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupcion by the conſeruacion of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayuer the holy goſte / the pſalmiſte ſaynge
/ He was not lefte in hell / that is / he was not lefte ded in erthe whiche is the vttermoſt malediccion for ſyn. nor his fleſſhe dyd not ſe corrupcion.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>13.</hi> Act. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> O iniquite moſt ſynfull / that they ſhuld thus prefere that falſſe god and in hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyt abowe al that is ſayd god / or that is worſhypyd / ſo that he ſyttyt in the temple of God and ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth him felffe as if he were god. Nowe whothere owre clargy be gylty in this thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / youge you that be lernyd. For they ſay wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue ſayd / This is mi body / which ☞ they call wordis of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecracion / or elſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge
/ which ſayd they ſay ther is no brede lefte / but it is the body of owre lorde / and
<pb facs="tcp:5270:19"/>ther is nothynge lefte but a hepe of acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall thyngis / as whyghtnes / rowndnes / ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer / touchyng &amp; ſychotere / which if it be ſo / then that thynge which to day is not ſhalbe God to morowgh / &amp; that thynge whych is with owte ſpryte or lyffe / groynge in the fyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de by kinde ſhalbe God anothere yere / which God we confeſſe to be with owt beginnyng or endynge / and in his manhede begottyn / and not made / as ſcriptur teſtifyth.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>1.</hi> Luc. <hi>1.</hi> Ebre. <hi>1.</hi> Pſal. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> For if his manhede were mad and increſyd dayly to the quantyte of theyre brede and wynne which they ſpend dayly in that vſe / he ſhulde ☜ were in on day be cart lodis more then he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in .xxxiij. yers whan he was here in erthe.</p>
               <p>But to be ſhorte if ony makyt in thes wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis / This is mi body / he muſte be perſon of Chriſt or elſe theyr is a falſe God / if it be the pryſtis body it is the body of a falſſe loſtell / a dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man / a theffe / a lecherere or of ſom othere ſynnere / and then there is vnclen bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / for any man to worſhope for God. If it be ony fleſh and blude it muſt nedis be the pryſtis body / fore in all holy ſcripture from the beginnyng of Geneſis to the ende of the Apocalypſe / there be no wordis writtyne of the makynge of Chriſtis body / but there be
<pb facs="tcp:5270:20"/>writtyne that Chriſt was the ſonne of the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>there / conſayuyd of the holy goſte / toke fleſh and blude of the virgin Mary &amp; that he dyde &amp; a roſe agen from deth the therde day with owt corrupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; that he aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyd in to heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s very God and man / and that we ſhulde bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in all ſcripture that is wryttyn of him / &amp; that he is to cum to Iuge bothe quyke &amp; ded and that the ſame Ieſus Chriſtis kynge and ſauyure / lord and makere of all thingis as is ſhowde in Geneſis.<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and if popyſch preſtod can not make that he made viſibill and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibyl / with all othere thinge wordly hauinge the wordis that he made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with / how ſhuld he make then Chriſt Ieſus of a pece of brede or of a drawght of wynne / of whome they er made / &amp; with owte whom they cane not ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue / moue / or be / Mor ouer you haue no wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of actorite thys to do but as you haue fur gyde of your on hedis as you haue don all othere thyngis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Godis lawe.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> Then ſum mane wolde ſay it a pere you do ſpecke a genſte the Sacramente / which owre forne fathers wyſe and well lernyd / and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t kyngis / emperurs / &amp; rulers with al other degres hath beleuyd and worſhipyd as god. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwere / I hold with the ryght honore of
<pb facs="tcp:5270:20"/>God / which is in veryte and truth / and with the lordis ſupper as ye ſhal knowe here after in his proper place / but I ſpecke only a genſt the myſuſe there of / which is to the grett diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor of God.<note place="margin">Not well myn inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.</note> in as mych / they make an y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll ſuply Godis preſence which he dyd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute in remembraunce / by cauſe they wold haue vs worſhope a creature in ſted of the makere.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſum wyl ſay / it is meruyll they dyd not ſpy this thynge / this falſnes / if it be true.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <note place="margin">Danie. <hi>9</hi>
                  </note> We anſwere that it is no meruyll / that God wyl haue / and ſuffere to his grett hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. For we rede in the old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t howe ther was an ydoll a monge the Babylony this whos name was Bell / this ydoll dyd the kynge worſhope dayly / in offeryng much flowere / wynne and ſhepe / ſuppoſyng that ydoll to ett all that dayly for the loue of hys worſhyppers / ontyl Danyel dyd ſhoue hym it was an ydolle and no lyuyng god / &amp; then whan the kynge had prouyd the truth by Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyels couſell
/ and fownd his wordis true &amp; the pryſtis worke and wordis falſſe / then he dyd put the ydoll to Danyelis iugme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te / and dyd ſle the pryſtis which in numbere were lx. &amp; .x. beſyde wyues &amp; chyldren. Therfor no meruel thowgh owr forne fathers be deſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd / 
<pb facs="tcp:5270:21"/>for why they had not Danyell wyth them / that is / they had not the iugment of God printyd in theyre hertis / they had not the knowlege of his verite by which they ſhuld leren to humbyll them ſelues to his ryghtwyſnes and iugment and lerne to are his mercy / they dyd worſhope Bell / that is / dyd beleue olde tradicions / popyſtical laws and ſectis / they beleuyd in ydolis / whiche as I ſayd be for ar nothyng in the thingis of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture / but workyng clene a genſt all natural thynge / euer folowynge theyre one fancy / which flowth &amp; ebbeth after theyre on wyll / makynge a thynge good whan they wyll / But nowe that owre kynge Henry the
.viij. whos lyffe I pray Gode longe to contynue / haue Danyell wyth him ye and printyd in his herte lett not vs dowt / but that his grace ſhal put this forſayd Bell to the iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Danyell that is godis worde which ſhal dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry him by the ſpryte of his mowght / And as for Belis pryſtis his grace ſhal ſle / which do deuowere dayly innumerabyl / mell / and wyne / and ſhepe / that is vnder the falſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of this falſſe ydole forſayd / do deuowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re meny ſimpyll ſowlis ſpiritally / and cauſe meny to fare herdly corporally / by theyr ſum<note place="margin">Daniel ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfyth the iugment of god / or kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wlege of his verite.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Bell ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyt olde tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicide and ceremonye.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Owr prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce haue Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niell wyth him and he ſhall dyſtry falſe Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes do Daniel the grettydolis</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:21"/>tuus / and ydyl profeſchion that they thowe owtwerdly. Wherfor as towchyng the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thes to ydolis / lett vs al dayly pray the wyl of owre lord to be fulfyllyd / &amp; to ſaue his tru minyſter owre ſuppreme hed ymmediatly vnder Chriſt kyng Henry the viii. &amp; owre nobyle prince Edwerd his ſon / with all his nobyl counſell. But ye ſhall not that the lorde wherby he might declare more plainly how grettly he abhoryt al infidelyte and ydolitre / dyd ade to thes two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis / him ſelf to be owre lorde God / ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and louynge / which viſyth the iniquite of fathers a ponne the ſonnes in the thyrd and fowrthe generacion / in thos which hate his name / neuertheleſſe / he do marcy in tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wſantis / to them which loue him &amp; kepe his preceptis / As who ſay / I am your God me you ſhal fare and loue / to me only you ſhall eleue / if ye beleue and worſhope ony othere God beſyde me / I ſhall reuenge that ſynne from tyme to tyme / but ſhall ſhow marcy &amp; benyngnite perpetually to them which loue me / and kepe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementis / that is in knowlingynge owre on infirmite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenynge only to his mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="commandment">
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:22"/>
               <head>¶ The thyrde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment.</head>
               <head type="sub">Thow ſhall not take the name of the lord God in vayne.</head>
               <p>WHos ſence is this. In as mych God owt to be faryd &amp; louyd of vs (as we heue ſhowde before) therfor we may not abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe his holyname / but muſt magnifyit a bowe al thingis / and alſo glorify it / in all thingis / as well in welght as wo / &amp; ſo only ſeke him with al owr mende / geuyng thankis to him for all thingis which chaunce from his hand. Fordermore we muſt kepe owre ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyly from all his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumely and blaſſemy / we may not name or ſpeke otherwich of him then becumyth his hy mayeſte. Alſo we may not vſe his holy name / in other vſes / then in thos which he wyll to be borne / for that is to his grett diſhonore and polutyng of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Wherfor (as meny clarkes ſay) by this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is forbydyne / necromancy / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geringe of deuellis / with othere ſych which God for byd to be vſyd / by cauſe they diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore his blyſſayd nam. But why wyll not they nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bere with the forſayd thingis / theyre ſayntifyd marchauntis and congeracions / as off myghtters / ryngis / croſyerſiaues / and with al othere robys / with owt which
<pb facs="tcp:5270:22"/>they thinge them ſelues no buſhops / alſo the congeracions which they vſe in makinge of popyſch pryſtis in ſharyng / puttynge on of veſtme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis / and in theyre uwyntingis in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loynge of bellis / cherchys of ſtone / chapels / auters / ſuperaltarys / with meny othere thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges wherby the honore of Godis name is more diſhonoryd / then by the forſayd conge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers / for they vſe theyre arte preuily with fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re leſt they ſhuldbe courrecte gettynge theyre lyuinge contrary to Godis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente but popyſſche preſtod with the holl ſorte of Antichriſte do not gett theyre lyuinge only falſly by theyr congeracions gretly diſhone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge Godis name / but alſo they ſubdwe by theyre craffe the holy name of God and lyue by opyne robry / yn ſhedinge off innocentes blude / ye as I ſayd before boſte them ſelues as God.<note place="margin">Popyſch blyſſynges is cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Popiſche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er worſſe then cunge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rere.</note> But ye ſhall not &amp; welmarke that ☜ the eternalle veryte can not be diſhonoryd more greuuſly than whane a wyttnes of fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhede is callyde to teſtify of his glory and na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. As conſernyng iuramentis / othes / and wous / howe greuuſlly is the name of God diſhonoryd of the ſelfſame linege / which pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meſſe meny hy thingis as mene grettly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardynge Godis honore and hytt dyde the
<pb facs="tcp:5270:23"/>Iuys neuer more diſhonore to his name / then they do. The Iuys were blynd / but they ſe &amp; wyll not ſe. Fyrſt lett vs begynne with owre horly fathere Pope / and ſo deſcende to ſere Ihon ſingyl ſowll / or ſere Antony lakla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn / and take of euery on a ſnache for I can not towche ther as they be worthy thowgh / I had Eraſmuſe cloques / and Swinglius ſprytt godly / I fere nothinge / but that I ſhal not tel the troth they ere ſo nawghtty and ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſticyuus.<note place="margin">Pope.</note> Owr horly father Pope howe dewoutly do he ſware and bynde him ſelffe by his office / to be true in confeſſinge the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of the trinyte / beyng crownyd with .iij. crowns which he take in tokyne of theſame othe / but how iuſtly do he kepe this iurame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whan in all his actis he clayme the offyce of owre ſauyure / and vſe him ſelffe as no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſer / but as a ſauyure to the gret diſhonore of the trinyte in aſmych he diſtry the merytis of Chriſtis blude which is owre only ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion / and helthe.</p>
               <p>Legattis alſo de latronibus I wold ſay de latere / they cleue ſo faſt to his ſyd (men as the ſay for the Popys noſe / opholders of his greciuꝰ mayeſte) loke in what iugme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he do fall they muſt nedys aſſociat him in the ſame</p>
               <note place="margin">Legattis.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:23"/>
               <p>Cardinalis alſo on whos neckis &amp; ſhowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hang the gattis of ſente Peters heuen / with a ſolome iurament clothyd with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de garment promiſſe to be redy always to ſhed theyr blud for Chriſtis veryte / but they fulfyllyt in ſhedyng other mens blud telling the trothe.<note place="margin">Cardinale</note>
               </p>
               <p>Archebuſhops alſo with theyre heuy croſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſis / do lykewyce ſware to bere the croſſe of chriſt in takinge payns to go &amp; prech the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt / &amp; always to be redy to ſoffere for theſame / do wel performyt in layng the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on othere mens bakis and neckis / and in cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifynge them that precke the trute
/ of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis merytis.<note place="margin">Archebuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Othere playn Buſhops alſo with theyr forkyd caps / promiſſe ſolemly to vphold &amp; ſtandby the olde teſtament and the nwe / ye and with them a genſt al herify to fyghte &amp; in tokyn of theſame toke that cape / and by cauſe the old teſtament and nwe / wore hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys of humilyte / which wyll more ſoffere then do ingery / therfor forgyttinge theyr othe &amp; iurament to wyne a ſynnere with me kenes / they haue abiecte the hornes of God / and only fyght with the hornys of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man bull and cruelly with them nowe they<note place="margin">Buſhope.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:24"/>fyght. But tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kis be to the lorde / they haue ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge goryd men thorowgh the rybis that a man can ſcaſe knowe the Roman bull froz Arons calfe / his hornys be ſo ſhorte and tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly they lake but a lytyll ſtobblynge.</p>
               <p>☞ Suffryd cranys / abbottis / with othere old fornicators fathers of dennes which make a grett woue with and othe to geue inſpectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theyre flocke / &amp; in tokyn therof take theyr croſſyer ſtaffe in ſtede of a ſhepperdis croke / but the ſyluer way ſo heuy at the fyrſt reſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge / that theyre hand is euer lame after wordis to do ony good worke accordyng to ☞ theyr promiſſe.<note place="margin">Croſſyere ſtafe.</note> What ſhal we ſay to the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe nons / which er maryd / ye for ſothe ſere Ihon ſay / to ſente Rateren / or ſanete all a ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry / and in tokyng they ſhalbe good to theyr ſere Ihon / the ware a rynge ſignifynge theyr ☞ peruers lyuinge.<note place="margin">Rynges.</note> What ſhal we ſay to all othere orders in generall / which promiſſe to lefte vp theyre hertis and mendis euer to he uene and to diſpyſſe al worldly dignytis / in tokyne therof they ſhaue theyre crowne all bere / but they take ſuch a cold at the fyrſte ſhauinge that they can neuer lefte theyr hert and mend from the erth and erthly thyngis after werdis.<note place="margin">Shauene crownes.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:24"/>
               <p>What thinke you by ſere Antony laklate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / which take a pone him to prech &amp; teche the goſpell of Chriſt and always to attend to the ſtody of Godes worde / how ſubſtaun cially do he diſcharge his office trwe ye in haukinge and huntinge ſhotinge and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge and ſuch othere good hyſtoris and lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs / which cownte ſcripture hereſy / and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre holines.<note place="margin">S. Antony</note> Ye but what ſay ye to ſere Ihon ſingyl ſowle / which wyll ſocke Chriſt owt of his fingers endis / ye for a peny plucke a ſowle owt of purgatory if he were herd ther to / which whan he is att his maſſe can not rede the goſpel if the candell be owt / by the Popis lawe / nor tellyt in englyſh whan it is lyght / Which if he lake his fanell in holding vp his handis at the Pater noſter or in ony othere lyke thinge / he is in dowght whothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re he hath mad his Godis body or no / by cauſe he lakyd the vertue of his fanell / or ſtole / but to deſyre his nayghbors wyffe or mayd in ſaynge Dominus vobiſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis ſalutaribus moniti / that is no faute / for euery man cane do ſo as wel as he / with meny othere qualites innumerabyll / which er not good but deteſtabyll.<note place="margin">S. Ione.</note> Nowe all thes thingis conſyderinge / we may ſe howe gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nnſly
<pb facs="tcp:5270:25"/>the name of God is blaſphemyd by theyre yuramentis &amp; falſe othes / vnder the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Godis glory / whan theyre ynſpec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon is only yn thyre bely and nothynge in the glory of godis name / as theyr dedis ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we yn all thyngis. There is noman truly ☞ which owt to vſurpe ony trwe othe or yura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / but that the glory of God &amp; neceſſyte of owre nayghbure ſhal require.<note place="margin">The cauſe of ſwaring</note> They popi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchers do not only blaffeme the name of god by theyre othes &amp; iuramentis / but alſo yn al actis &amp; dedis they er a genſt the profyth and welthe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be in gret neceſſite / And thes forſayd cauſis ercepte / al kynd of othes ere forbidiue / as the wordis of Chriſte do te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyfy &amp; teche vs / whych whyll that all owre ſermone be / is is. no no. and that which is more he teſtifyth to be of yll.<note place="margin">Math<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5</note> By this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment we may not vſurpe ony othe by owre proper and priuate temeryte. And ye ſhall not / that the turament and othe which we geue the mayeſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundinge and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge / is by no mens agenſt this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / by caus in a nother place of ſcripture he geuyt them powre ſo to do and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde.<note place="margin">Owre kyn ge co naun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingewe er bownde to ſware. <hi>1</hi> Reg. <hi>7</hi>
                  </note> Wherfor he that diſpyſe his prince / he that wyll not knowlege him his hede (as all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtis
<pb facs="tcp:5270:25"/>wyll not) they breke this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te / &amp; gretly diſhonore the glorius name of Gode / for kyngs truly er his true myniſters yn this cherch mylitante / and ther is no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſupplith nerte to Chriſte but o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thei / al othe re powrs that be yn erth / be of them / as du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kis / bernes / lordis / knyghtis / apoſtels / Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / &amp; ſuche lyke / where fore they that reſiſte there kynge / &amp; them of hym ſente / reſyſt the ordinance of God.<note place="margin">Rome. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Euery man is fubdude to thes hyer powrs as Peter teſtifyt ſaynge / be ye ſubyecte to euery huma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creature for God other to the kynge as moſt ercellent / or to the dukis as of hym ſente / to the vengaunce of ill doers / to the laude truly of God doers / A ducke properly is callyd a leder / gyde / or dyrecter. And ye ſhall nott that a Chryſtyn kynge / may not only prouyd gydis for a po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lytyke order / but alſo for a ſpyrytall order / wherfor he hathe powre to ynſtytute gydis of diuers vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / whych gydis then er bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wnd to vſe them ſelues accordynge to theyr vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The polytical rulers to vſe theyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficis with mercy and iuſtis / that is in may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenyng the good / &amp; correctynge the yll. The apoſtolicall minyſters / and dyaconicall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of them to vſe theyre office with all truth
<pb facs="tcp:5270:26"/>and humylyte / ſo ſhynyng with worde and dede that all men myght glorify the heuenly fathere in heuen in folowyng theyr doctrine &amp; good liuinge.<note place="margin">The Pope hath byne euere age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the Chriſte of Gode.</note> And ye ſhal not that by thes forſayde wordis / ye may perſayue the Pope and his ſecte hath longe diſhoneryd his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / in kepinge true hedis vnder his fytte. If ſente Peter (of whom he claym his prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) dyd obay kyngis and rulers (as owre ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyure Chriſt do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and dyde beynge a chylde and a man as it is playn in ſcripture) wher lerne he thys pryd &amp; whare hath he his auctorite to clayme &amp; hold his primacy ouer al the worlde?<note place="margin">Luc. 2. Math. 9.</note> Truly he hathe it of the world and deuell / This herde perchance ſum papiſt wyll ſay / that I ſpeke agenſte cherite / by cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe he toke his auctorite by counſente of the cherche / grett Conſtantyne beynge Empo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore of Rome / as the ſcripture of the cherche do teſtify.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <note place="margin">Two ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturs.</note> To this I anſwere / that there is two ſcripturs / that is / the ſcripture of God and ſcripture of man / the Lordis is immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byl / and dampnabyl to the brekers / mans is mutabyl and not dampnabyl to the brekers / the on that is Godis muſt nedis be. the othe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re if it wornet it wore the better. The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God is ſo neceſſary that it can not be
<pb facs="tcp:5270:26"/>augmentyd ne myniſchede (as ſcripture teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fy) with owt dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of body and ſowle / The ſcripture of mane is myniſchyd &amp; aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentyd euery day after the ymaginacion of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s brayne / whych nott kepte puryfyth the ſowle / bet ofte tymes bryngeth dethe to the body
/ of whych ſcrypture Polle byd vs take hyd / callynge it the doctrine of deuels &amp; fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fs antichriſtis / wherfore to this falſe ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re chriſten men ere nott bownde / but to the ſcripture of God ye &amp; we muſt kepe al thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis that er wryttne ther in with al the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilite that we can / for in it is wrytting and ſhowde althyngis neceſſary for owre redem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / accordinge to the prophicy of the holy goſte ſpekinge by the pſalmiſte of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Syon / that is of the true ſpeculacion of God and his Chriſt / ſaynge. The Lord ſhall ſhowe / vnderſtande all thyngis pertayninge to his true honor of his Chriſte / in ſcripturs of pepyll and princes whiche haue byne in it in the true contemplacion of Godis worde / and that is the olde Teſtament and nwe / he ſay not / The Lorde ſhall ſhowe in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs of pepyll and princis that nowe be in Syon / but in the ſcripturs of them that hate byne / in it. Therfor by chauſe we er co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyd
<pb facs="tcp:5270:27"/>in meny placis of ſcripture to obay owr princis / and can fynde in no place the Pope
/ therfor we may affirme al kyngis with they<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re miniſters to be the true electe hedis vnder God / the Pope and his ſecte to be very enny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of the croſe of Chriſt very Antichriſtis agenſt God and name.<note place="margin">Scripture comman<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vs to obay owrekynge but not the Pope.</note> Therfore lett all men be obedient to theyre princis / and we in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to owre kynge Henry the .viij. moſt exce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lente and faythfull myke paciente and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy full / beynge a moge vs (as the Lorde com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde) as on of vs / always wyllynge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundinge that thynge in his cherche and ſubiectis / which is to the glory of God and Ieſu Chriſte / always co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that which is to the commoune and not to his proper welthe / but god knoweth he hath meny a ſlo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we workere in fulfylling this his wyll. Age<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne howe marcyful he is agenſt his rebellers. What ſtody what payne do his grace take dayly to ſett forte God glory? In what ieber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; hate is he of the worlde for the loue of Godis worde? Othere kyngis take ſtody to increſſe theyr ſubiectis with ryches worldly. ☞ Our kynge do not increſſe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with worldly ryches only / but alſo &amp; chefely with the worde of God which is better then gold
<pb facs="tcp:5270:27"/>and precyuus ſtons. What infideles wold rebel and be falſe agenſt ſuch a prince hauyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the qualitys and vertws that he hath? we owt therfore to be true and louynge to him and his / by nature and kynde / ye and much more by the laue of God / by the which lawe alſo he hath bowde vs / ye &amp; we haue all ſwor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in the holy name of owre lorde God to be true to him &amp; his laufull hayers / to the grett glory of Godis name &amp; tranquilite of hys reme. Therfor to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clud lett all men take he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ☜ vnto theyre othe / which euery man may laufully vſe (as Paul dyd) in affirmyng the dignite of the goſpelle and glory of Godis name / and lett them inſtructe theyr chyldren in tyme of youte / that they may laerne to know God and theyre Prince / and no more to be blyndly lede as they haue byne a fore this tyme / in rebelling agenſt theyre Prince.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roma.</hi> 1.</note> By this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement alſo we er bownde to cal a pone non othere name whan neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſhal compell / but a pon the name of Gode / for it pertayn only to his glorye / that he be had an vnicall wyttnes and record of verite / which is the vnical and eternall helthe &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.<note place="margin">we er bownde to ſware only by God for the trwth.</note> Therfor a way with owre ladyſe bedyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men / Auguſtinis / Dominickis / Benedictis
<pb facs="tcp:5270:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſcans / Baſylighttis / the .v. diſcordis of the cherch as Tomyſtis do ſay / a way with thes and all other ſectis the dropingis of the deuylis tayll / the vpholſters of Antichriſt the ſon of perdicion / And that he myght the better inculke to vs this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement dyd adde thes wordis / that he wold reuenge him ſelffe agenſt all them which dyd take his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name in vayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="commandment">
               <head>¶ The fowrth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment.</head>
               <p>Remember the Sabott day / that thou ſanctify theſam / ſex days tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſhalte worke / and ſhal do all thy beſynes / the .vij. day is the Sabott day of the lorde God / Thow ſhalt do non of they workes / thow and thy ſonne / and dowghter / thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and handmayd / thy beſt and pylgram whych is in thy portis / For in .vj. days thy Lord dyd make heuen and erth / the ſee and al thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gis gis which er in them / and the .vij. day he dyd reſt / therfor he dyd blyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyt and ſanctify the ſame.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:28"/>
               <p>THe obſeruacion of the Sabott day do pertayn alſo to the honore and worſho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe of God / in as much it is contaynid vnder the fyrſte tabyl and is nominate the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion of the day / Wherfor God dyd require neuer nothynge more ſtrayghtlye to be ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pte / And whan he wold ſignify by Prophet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis al religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubuerſt / and good lyuinge ſett parte / he dyd euer ſay his holydays to be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutyd / on halowyd / vyolatyd / not kepte / not ſanctifyd / as thowght this obedience omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyd and lefte / nothynge remaynyd be ſyde / in which he myght be honoryd.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. <hi>Nume.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.</note> Truly ther is no dowght but that this precepte was a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyd to the Iuys for the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of ceremonys / that it myght repreſente the ſpiritall worſhype of God / vnder the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall obſeruacion to them / Wherfor in the commynge of Chriſt / which is the ende and the lyght of ſhadowes / &amp; the truth of figurs this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement was diſtryde / as other ſhadows of Moyſis lawe / lyke as Paull do teſtify euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 4. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.</note> But neuertheleſſe we (the ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonys diſtryde / &amp; the externall couſtome / by which in the berke of the lawe / that is / in the letter the Iuys fayth was excerſiſyd) do hold the truthe of this precepte / which te lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:5270:29"/>wyl to be perpetuall / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune to the Iuys and vs / which truthe is this. to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re &amp; loue God a boue all thynge / &amp; to pute owre confidence and quiettnes only in him / which then ſhalbe doune wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal refrayn with owt colore from owre concupiſcencys &amp; yll deſeyris / which do nothynge els / but breke the mende from God / ver and turmoyll owr ſpryth.<note place="margin">The kepin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of the holy day.</note> Alſo whan we ſelfe from the vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitabyll workis of owre fleſhe / that is which<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er ſpronge of owre concupiſcence and wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chydnes of nature / ye to be ſhorte whan we refrayn from all workisco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the ſpryte of Gode / althowgh they bere be fore them ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſimilitude of mans prouidens / and wytte / For thes manner of workis be all ſeruiall / from which the lawe byd vs to ſeſſe in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>botday / that God myght dwell in vs / worke that good is and gouerne vs by the mens of his holy ſpryt by whos mens he geuyth the rem / pece / &amp; tranquilyte of conſchiens.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ieſa.</hi> 35.58. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencions is bondage. Ihon. <hi>14.</hi> Ephe <hi>3. 1.</hi> Corin. <hi>3.</hi> Roma. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> This truly is the true Sabott day / whos forme &amp; ſhadowe was theſame iudaycall.<note place="margin">The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bott day is to haue the ſpryt of god in owre her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes.</note> Therfor it was aſſinyd to the .vij. day which numbere hath ſignificacion of perfection in ſcripture / wherby we ere towght God to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende and geue a pertuell Sabat day to vs / which ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:5270:29"/>ende by no terme or tyme / alſo that lyuinge we ſhall not ſanctifyth plentuuſly and after a iuſte ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner / on tyll the ſeuenth day / which is the laſt and eternall day / for althowgh we haue begone to enter in to his ſabott day by fayth / hyt we ſhall not cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the plentuuſnes ther of / tyl the reſurrection of owre mortall bodys / and whan we ſhall ſe God face to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce as he is.<note place="margin">The trwe Sabot day is not yn this lyffe.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebreo.</hi> 4. <hi>Roma.</hi> 8. 1. <hi>Ihon.</hi> 4.</note> Nowe therfor by fayth we haue begone owre quiettnes in God / in which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we do dayly make progreſſe / that then at the laſte we may profytte whan theſame of Iſay is fulfyllid in which a day of reſte from a day of reſte is promiſſyde to the cherch of God / that is / wher now they ſe him by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culacion of fayth / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhal ſe him in ded / wher nowe we hold his ſhadowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal poſſeſſe his ſubſtaunce.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 1. <hi>Corin</hi> 15. <hi>Gene.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">The ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day is not made to be halo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wid wither clamacion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but wyth the Lordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worde. Gala. <hi>4.</hi> Coloſ. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> That which partayn to the ſonday / which we do obſerue nowe is not inſtytute therfor that we ſhuld ſanctify the ſame a boue other days / and thynkyt mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re holy / for all holynes is the ſingulere prero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatyue of God only / which dyd honor all days a lyke. But that the cherche myght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togethere in that day to prayers and lawdis of God / to here the worde of God / &amp; to vſe the Sacramentis in rygijt order (which as it
<pb facs="tcp:5270:30"/>er owt of order) in which thyngis that we myght the beter apply al owre ſtody / we ſhuld ſeſſe from manual workis / and from al impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ttis / which pertayn to the reſon of his lyffe / that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worde of God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyd purly and ſyncerly (as it is but of fewe) then we myght reſayue the ſame with a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ete mend and a faythfull hert / w erby we myght mortify / the workis of the olde Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſanctifynge not only that day / but alſo euery day in the wek e / And ye ſhall not that we whiche ere faythfull owt not to diſcerne by twyne day and day / but for the cauſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune polyſy as is ſhowde before.<note place="margin">Diſcernin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of days is forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge</note> Therfor holy days er not aſcribyd and ordainyd / that we ſhuld honore God by ſeſynge of workis whereby men gett theyre bodyly ſuſtinans / iuſtly and after Godis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement / but by cauſe the cherich ſhulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>together in ſum day to lerne in herynge Godis worde howe to fede the ſowle / Which thynge not towght men were better to kepe theyre byſynes at home accordinge to theyre vocacions / that is rulers to ſtody for the commune profytte poore men to labore for theyr lyuinge / then for to cum to the perſons barne / and there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myt ydolitre in mayntenynge his ambiſion / <note place="margin">If Godes worde be not towght me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>were bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cherch.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:30"/>pride / and beſtly lyuinge. Nobyl ſtatis were better to hunte the bull here / hert or ony othe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re thynge lyke intendinge to ſuckure the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wre with the mette / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to here ſere Ihon ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyl ſowle ſtombel a payer of matte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in late<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſlynge holy water / curſe holy brede / and to play a caſte kyke yack an napes in a foles cot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. But I wold God all men were as redy to do / to folowe and here the worde of God / which is very Chriſt Ieſue / accordynge to Godis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement and owre Princes / as they er to do / folowe and here the word of Antichriſt which is the deuyll himſelffe / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundyd by the Lord of the worde and ſone of perdicion. And ye ſhal knowe this day or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinyd for a godly polyſy / is nowe vſyd to the grett diſhonore of God / ſo that it were better to be vſyd neuer a dell / ye not to be had in remembraunce / wherby men myght wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / then to vſe it as they do for the moſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.<note place="margin">The body of Chriſt is mad the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy of an hee lott for la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of true techynge.</note> Nowe the worde of God is not purly &amp; ſyncerly towght / but in fewe placis / nor can not be truly towght it is ſo ſnarlyd by popy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſche loſels / and with theyre popyſche ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nys / Nowe meny men and women for lake of good techynge do prepare the; ſelues mor for to be ſene then to lerne / ſhoynge themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb facs="tcp:5270:31"/>in the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion more lykere ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neriall perſons thene true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſt / and makytt more lykere a fayer and pray fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the deuell then a body ſekynge the glory of theyre hede Chriſt Ieſue / &amp; ſuppoſe that ſo diſgyſſyd to halowe the ſabot day / folowin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge popyſch preſtod / &amp; Iſydis pryſtis which inwerdly deturpede / ſanctify that day more by owtwerd garmentis folis cottis and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kis comes / then by true doctryn.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> And thus ☞ if men wold well marke the effecte of owre ſabot day and the myſuſes ther of I truſt the mokis of ſophyſtryans ſhuld vaniſch cleue a vay which hath ſcateryd the worlde full of iudaycall opinions / which ſay that the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement muſt be abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate which ceremony they call in theyre ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the taracion of the .vij. day / but that thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge which is morall / that is that thyng which pertaynd to theyre maners do remayn ſtyll to vs / and that is the obſeruacion of on day / which day they only chonge in the contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Iuys.<note place="margin">Markethe godly ſprite of owre ſtol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le mene.</note> But you haue herd what profyt cum by ſuch a doctryne. For they cleuynge only to theyre conſtitucion and decreſſe / as the Iuys to the barke of the lawe / that is the letter hath &amp; do diſhonore God more a .M.
<pb facs="tcp:5270:31"/>tymes thene the Iuys dyd / in brekynge the ſabot day / that is in cauſynge meny to er fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true fayth of owre ſauyur Chriſt Ieſue / nethere reſpectynge the fruifulnes &amp; profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the ſame towerdis owre naybours and othere creaturs laboryng for vs / nor it the effecte there of as I ſhowd before / in reſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge the true worde of God.</p>
               <trailer>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Here ende the .iiij. commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis contaynyd in the fyrſt tabyll / &amp; they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrybe after what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner we ought to be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue owr ſelues towers God / which well mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyd do vtterly condempne vs and dreue vs to ſelfe helpe of Chriſt only which is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the lawe
/ that is of owre iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion / ryghtwyſnes and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to whom be all honore and glory as it haue byne is / and ſhalbe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we and euer.</trailer>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="commandment">
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:32"/>
               <head>The fyfthe ¶ The fyfthe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement.</head>
               <head type="sub">Honor thy fathere and mothere.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N thes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementis precedyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is declaryd the obedience and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore / the fare and loue that we muſt bere towerdis God and his gloryus name / and to his minyſters which er ordinyd of him (as I ſhowede you before in the .iij. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement) to the coſeruacion of theſame. which er not ordinyd to reſpecte &amp; rule theyr proper howſolde only / and to ſe it inſtrute and towght accordynge to Godes lawe / but chefly they muſt inſpecte the vniuerſall cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of God ouere which they be inſtitute / he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis / duckis and buſhops / euer aduertyſtynge that thynge to bedone which is to the glory of his name. This don he adde particulere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementis which alſo we er bownde to kepe.<note place="margin">Prouer. 1. Leui. 19.</note> Therfor in as mych we er bownde to ſere and loue God we may not neglecie owre parentis
/ or offende them in ony thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / but we muſt fare and worſhope them / we muſt obay them vnder the wyll of owre Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / we muſt ſtody to pacyfy &amp; cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente them / in all ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of thyngis that owre workis may do them good / and to thez that do thus
<pb facs="tcp:5270:32"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> benediction is addyd / that is / to leue longe a pon thys erthe / to haue the benediction of worldly thynges a pone erthe. The which promyſſe declare howe acceptabyll the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of owre parentis is to God / alſo that it myght moue and ſtere owre ſlugyſnes to be redy to this obedience / ye and to loke for malediccion if we do the contrary. And ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al not this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement is a particulere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>maundement for the carnall father &amp; ſone / and by nomens can ſuffere an allegory or po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſche morall. Not withſtandinge meny (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to theyr qualytes) do rowle in theyr allegorys / but to ſay the trothe / in allegacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s popiſticall / vpholdynge by theyr ſophyſtical ſciencis by falſe colers of hypocriſy the hore of Gabylon the venemyſſe dragone / a genſt whom they haue ſworne the contrary owre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt nobyll Prince commaundinge. Whan t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey haue declaryd the duty of the fathere &amp; carnall ſon and ſhowe howe euery father is not only bownd to brynge vpe his ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an honeſte carnal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner / but alſo after a goodly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner / then they adde lyke true cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of antichriſt / howe all men owt to obay alſo by this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementis theyr ſpiritall fathers / conwtynge themſelues as hedis &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5270:33"/>no minyſters as geuers of grace and not as reſayuers / the popys angelis / and not apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels ſente by theyre hedde Godis tru miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter / as theyr one wordis do teſtify / They ſay all mene generally be bownde to obay them &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. as the carnall ſone is his father / there is no mane cane deny but that owre Prince is a mortall man / therfore as it a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re by theyre wordis he is bowde to obay buſhops / and ſere Ihon ſingyll ſowle / by cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe they be ſpiritall fathers / you that haue fayth iuge thes wordis well / I confeſſe all chriſtenne men to be ſpirituall / and chefly owre Prince in his vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Svicitalfa there er of the Dope / true miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters er of owre kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge.</note> For all perſons electe er moſt ſpiritall in vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / owre prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce truly is one electe / therfor he is moſte ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritall in vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">By vococio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be al ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere / but not fathers Ihon. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> This is prouyd by the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of Chriſt ſaynge. The ſhepe which the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>there haue goue me in my handes no man can take them a way from me / that is / the electe perſons no deuell or worldly thynge cane lett them from the true reſayuynge of my worde / by whych they ſhalbe made the chyldrene of Gode / in teſtimony of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and vertwe / And owre Prince (as it a pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re by his frutis) is not only knowe electe by thys mauner of callynge but alſo by his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſtracion<note place="margin">Ihon. 1. No mane is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oue owr Prince by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:33"/>and dignyte / as it a pere by thes wordis wryttyn in the boke of wyſdam / whare is ſayd / Myſdam is better then ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth corporall / and a prouydent man is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a ſtronge mane. Therfor Oye kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis here and vnderſtande / lerne o ye Iugis of the herth / geue are you that rule multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis / and ere ſuſtaynyd by the pepyll of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions / for powre is geuen to you of Gode goodnes &amp; vertwe of the all myghty / which ſhal proue your actis and iuge your thowgh tis &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Owre Prince therfor electe we may well affirme him to be moſt ſpiritall in voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion / Then why do they exclude him / wyth othere of his electe perſons &amp; ſubiectis from theyre ſpiritall nominacion.<note place="margin">Why do me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues a bone theyr hede.</note> If there be no buſhope or ſhulble but ſuch as owre Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce do admytt why do they members clayme ſyngularite a boue theyre Kyng which is theyr hed vnder Chriſte / which in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis cane ſoffere no ſingularite but al that he do / thynke or ſpeke is for the welth of the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le body / that is the holle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munallte / whos office is includyd in the thyrde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as I ſhowe before. And ye ſhal not that they<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er not only howlde to name themſelues ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritall but alſo they augmente this theyr ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallte
<pb facs="tcp:5270:34"/>with a fatherhede / whan Thriſt wyl that we ſhuld knowelege non but only the ſpirituall fathere in heuen / which can ſaue &amp; dampene vs / &amp; whan Chriſte do call al thos which do fulfyll this heuenly fathers wyll / his mothere / ſone &amp; brothere. Therefor theyr nominacion be no mens can betrwe / excepte it be for peruers doctrine / or by theyr on chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſytt by othere mens feyrs / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for lett it be wypyd owt of the Lordis ſede / for the Lorde can ſoffere no ſych ſede in his berne.<note place="margin">They be no fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut of othe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drene.</note> Therefor theyr nominacion be no mens can betrwe / excepte it be for peruers doctrine / or by theyr on chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſytt by othere mens feyrs / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for lett it be wypyd owt of the Lordis ſede / for the Lorde can ſoffere no ſych ſede in his berne.</p>
               <p>Alſo ye ſhalle nott that euery Man is bownd to brynge vp his chyldrene in lernyn of ſum good doctryne wherby they may kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we God / &amp; with ſum manuall worke or occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pacion / wherby they may gett theyre lyuyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge with the ſwett of theyre face. And by cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe euery maſter owt to bringe vp theyre chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren accordynge to the fathers wyll / therfor in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement is the maſter bownd to inſtrute his diſcipyl or ſeruante well / and accordynge to Godis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te / whos duty is ſhowd in meny placis of ſcripture.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Timo.</hi> 2. <hi>Colo.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Petri.</hi> 2.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="commandment">
               <head>¶ The .vi. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5270:34"/>
               <head type="sub">Thow ſhal not ſlee.</head>
               <p>THat is / in as mych God owthe to be louyd and faryd of vs / lett vs horte no man by ony manere of mens / nor it oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ony mane by violence / lett vs do noman yngery or wronge / but let vs be always / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy te ſhowe benyuolence to all men / bothe feyndis and ennymes / lett vs ſtody to pleſſe bothe / iff they be yn ony neceſſyte.</p>
               <p>Thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandiment wyl alſo that myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the worde / muſt not folowe falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine in kyllinge meny a ſowle / by theyre he riſy / and in ſleynge the body for tellynge tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="commandment">
               <head>¶ The .vij. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente.</head>
               <head type="sub">Thow ſhall do no fornicacion.</head>
               <p>THis commaundemente wyll that they which wyl fere and loue God / muſt ſo order themſelues
/ that they lyue chaſte and continent all the days of theyre lyffe. Alſo by cauſe vyrginyte is a ſingulere gyfte of God / lett euery man marke what is geuen to him.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iaco.</hi> 1.</note> For they which take not this worde / that is / haue not the gefte of chaſtyte / they
<pb facs="tcp:5270:35"/>haue a remidy offeride of God for the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of theyre fleſhe / and they that do not vſe that remidy reſyſte Gode and reſyſte his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Nor lett no man ſay (as meny do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we a days) to haue powre to do all thyngis helpyd by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of God / For the helpe of God is not preſent but only to them which walke in his ways / that is / in his vocacion / from which thes hypocritis do indeuer to drawe themſelues / agenſt the wyll of God / In this peuyſnes and preſumpcion lett not them loke for God to be a helper / but lett them rethere remembere / his ſaynge / thow ſhalte not tempte they lorde God. This tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is to tempte God / to indeuer and ercerſys agenſt nature / which is geuen to vs of him / ye &amp; ſo to diſpyſſe his preſente geftes.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>3.</hi> Nott what it is to tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pte Gode.</note> Thys godly gefte of nature the popyſche ſorte do not only diſpyſe / in miſuſynge themſelues agaynſte all nature abominabyll to ſpecke / but alſo the loſels er bowlde to call matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony a polucion which God whas worthy to inſtitute / which he dyd pronownſe hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabyll to all men / which owr ſauyure Chriſt dyd ſanctify by his preſence
/ garniſſyng the ſame with his fyrſte miracle / but with moſt ſotell ſtatutis / rulis
/ and decreſe / they do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll
<pb facs="tcp:5270:35"/>euery, zelycall vowe / and progreſſion / I ſhuld ſay euery celycall vowe &amp; profeſchion. As thowgh theyr ſcalde vowe wor not one / and virginyte a nothere / They call theyre ſtald vows / agelicall vertws / doynge great ingery to the angellis of God / to the which they compare laſſiuyous parſons / adulteres and ſum thynge moreworſſe and ſtinkynge.<note place="margin">Men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> more the pes ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cis then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des.</note> And truly we nede not to reherſſe more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyns / where the thynge ſelffe is manifeſte / we ſhall ſe truly by what grett and horribyll payns the lord ſhall reuenge thys arrogans and contempte of his gyftis. By this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo euery man is bownd to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and vſe his wyffe ſoberly / and gentilly / &amp; the wyffe lykewyce the man / further mor to that they ſhall admytt nothyng contrary to the honeſte and temperance of matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny / &amp; ſo doyng / they ſhall knowe at the laſte to mary in the Lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="commandment">
               <head>¶ The .viij. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement.</head>
               <head type="sub">Thow ſhalt do no thefte.</head>
               <p>Whych muſt thus be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / whan truly we owte to fare and loue Gode / lett vs deſayue no man othere be crafte or
<pb facs="tcp:5270:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>fraude / nor lett vs not take a way by hande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vyolence that which pertayne to hym / nor we may not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe ony man in bergo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nauntis / ſellynge a more hyere pryce or in baynge a more vylde pryce of thos which knoweth not the valure of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gis / or by ony othere acte &amp; crafte by which we do lay owr hadis in other mens goodis. But if the fare and loue of God be in vs / we wyll indeuer more with all owr powre to helpe both owr fryndis and foes / as much as ly in vs bothe by counſell and helpe in vpholdynge &amp; may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynnynge theyre bodys and goodis / ye and rethere to minyſch owr on goodis then to ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a way a nothere mans / not only that / but if they were oppreſt by the miſfortune of thyngis / we were bownd to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte owre goodis to the ſuſtentacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr neceſſytes / and to the alleuyacion of theyre nede by owre plentuuſnes. Lett all chriſtene men reſpecte to this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement in hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge the powre membris of Chriſtis body to the powre threſhers of the Lordis corne / to the powre creaturs which lake theyr natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall lymbys / and no more to vphold by obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions the grett ydolis of this worlde / that is Antichriſt with his preſtode / and all theyr<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 10. <hi>Ieſa.</hi> 58.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>grett godis / lett them no more hepe Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtis boxe / nor hyt is ſecte for all theyre gay mockis / but miniſter to Chriſt and his true floke as Chriſt do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund promiſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge a rewarde to al thos that grue a cope of water to the lefte of his miniſters / and diſci pilis for his names ſake.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roma.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="commandment">
               <head>¶ The .ix. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement.</head>
               <head type="sub">Thou ſhall beare no falſe witneſſe.</head>
               <p>THat is / whan thow owtis to fare and loue God ſe that thou duſt oppreſſe no man by falſe accuſation / nor thow ſhall not minyſſe no mans fame / by yll wordis / and raylynges / nor thou ſhall not geue thy aers to ſuch brawlers / nor thou ſhalte not ſuſpecte or iouge ony man to the worſte parte / or in the worſte ſence / but if there be ony fare &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue in vs we owte allways to thynke the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte / and to ſpeke honorably of euery man / &amp; to bere the weknes of euery man / as egall as is poſſibyl to the honor of gode and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall cherite in concernynge thynges par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulere which partayne to human affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and workis.</p>
               <p>And ye ſhall notte that all thos which vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.
<pb facs="tcp:5270:37"/>hold antichriſte and his ſectes whicher parti culere and belymaſters / geue falſe wytneſſe agaynſte the true body of Chriſt / in mainti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the body of an harlotte
/ that is / the ſecte of the hore of Babylone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="commandment">
               <head>¶ The .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement.</head>
               <head type="sub">Thou ſhalte not couyt they ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghbours houſe / thou ſhalt not deſeyre his wyfe / nor ſeruaunt / nor handmayd / nor oxe / nor aſſe nor nothynge that is his.</head>
               <p>WHerby owr Lord do teche vs which owt to loue and fere / that we may not couyt a mans wyfe / famele / poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or ony thynge els. By the which reſoue he do much more forbyd that we do not inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / by ony fraud ſotylte or crafte / ye all thowgh it be vnder the pretence of houeſte / by the which we ſhall cauſe the wyfe to forſake he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re huſbane / or take the ſeruaunte from the handis of the maſter / or take by vyole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ony perte of his goodis. But if ther be ony loue and fare of God in vs we owt more to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſch the loue of the man and wyfe / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge euery man to kepe his one wyfe and the
<pb facs="tcp:5270:37"/>wyfe here man / and to exhorte ſeruauntis to do theyr duty to theyre maſters / with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / &amp; to defend euery mans ryghte as much as lyth in vs.</p>
               <p>That truly we er for bydyne to couyt a no there ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s goodis thuſe may be takyne / that euery man owt to vſe him ſelfe to his ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghboure accordyne to the vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his-offi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and ſtate / He truly couyt a nother mans good which wyll not execute &amp; do thos thyn gis which he is bownd to do accordynge to the gefte of his callynge.<note place="margin">Not who is couyttus.</note>
               </p>
               <p>By this reaſon alſo the pepyll owt to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in mende theyre kyngis &amp; princis / maye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis &amp; othere rulers / and to ſuffere theyre do minacion by a quiette mend / to obay theyre laws and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementis and to ſlake in nothynge which is not contrary to God is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement.<note place="margin">The office of duckis &amp; lord is.</note> Agen they muſt ſuſtayn the cure and charge of theyre pepyll / reſtore the ryght / conſerue publyke pece and tranquily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / they muſt be in helpe to good / refrayners to the yll doers and ſo miniſter all thynge / as men beynge all ways redy to geue fore theyr office an anſwere to God the hy kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and iuge.</p>
               <p>Byſhops and miniſters of cherches lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:5270:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>lett them labore and ply faythfully in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſtracion of the worde / nor lett them not defyle the doctryne of helthe / but lett them geue the pure and ſyncere doctryn of God / and inſtructe men not only by doctryne but alſo by exampel of lyfe / &amp; ſo to geue inſpectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theyer ſhype / as good ſhypers to theyre ſhype / Agene the pepyll muſt knowe them for maſſengers and apoſtels of God / and to geue them that honore that the lord wyl thez to haue / and geue them thos thyngis which er neceſſary to the ſuſtentacion of theyr lyfe.<note place="margin">The office of byſhops.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">A byſhope owt to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no more but met dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke &amp; clothe. 1. Timo. 4. The office of pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Lett parentis take theyre chyldren as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittyd to thez of the Lorde / to be noryſſhyd / tought &amp; rulyde / nor lett not them vexe they re mendis by onkenùnes and ſtrayt gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and turne themſelues from them / but with lenyte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d gentylnes / and as it pertayn to theyr perſons / lett them amplecte and con forte them.<note place="margin">Iouth age.</note> Iunyers ſhall reuerently accepte old age / as God wyll it to be honoryd. Olde men alſo ſhall moderate by theyr wyll &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the imbeſilyte of youth / &amp; in that che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly / wher in they ſhyne &amp; haue knowlege by vſe of thyngis / not troblynge them by herd and clameurs reproues / but te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porynge theyr ſeueryte with all gentylnes / and fauere. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes
<pb facs="tcp:5270:38"/>ſhall geue them ſelues as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge theyr office beſy and obaynge theyr ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters / not ſeruynge to the eye / but with the herte / as geuynge theyre ſeruys to Gode.<note place="margin">Seruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Maſters.</note> Maſters alſo may not be curious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractabyl agaynſt theyre ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis / they ſhal not vexe them with much aſperyte / ne take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelyuſly / but rethere knowledge thez to be theyre brotheren / and ſeruauntis vnder the ſame Lorde which is in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whom they owte to loue and ſoffere in al manſwetneſſe. To this maner lett euery mane repute what he owthe to his neyboure in his order and place / and that he owe lett hym geue.</p>
               <p>We haue the holle lawe explicatt in .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes / by the whych we er ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently inſtructe of all thos thyngis / which the lorde do othere require of vs / or forbyde to be done / as well towerdis him ſelfe / as owre nayghbours. Truly it is eſy to perſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue to what ende all thyngis do intende / tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to teche cherite.</p>
               <p>But fyrſte we er inſtrute that we ſhulde fare / loue &amp; worſhope God / and haue confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence only in him / that we ſhuld call and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke him / and ſhold expecte and loke for all thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of him and ſhuld put owr hope only in
<pb facs="tcp:5270:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>him / ſhuld reſte in him / which is the ſum of the fyrſte tabyll / by which we er inſtrute on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to goodlynes and pyete.</p>
               <p>Fordere more we haue cheryte with owr neyghbours for godis ſake / ſo doynge with all men as we woldbe doune to / which is the hede of the .ij. tabyll. And thuſe it apere that the obſeruacion of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementis is / to loue only God and owr neyghboure / and he lyuyth moſt beſt &amp; holyeſt which as mych as is poſſibyll do not lyue and ſtody to him ſelfe / to his proper lukere and profyth / and a gene there is non that lyuyth more worſe &amp; wrethede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he which ſtody only to his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per luckere / ſeke and thynke only is one pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyth.</p>
               <p>ANd ye ſhall nott that the lawe do not forbyd only owtwerd werkis but alſo the in werde affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; thowgh of the herte. Ther be meny which do ordere theyr eyes / fytt / ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis and all partis of the body / in ſum obſeruacion of the lawe / but in the menſeſon they holde theyr hertis fare from all obedien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / they thynke themſelues goodworkers / if they haue diſſimulyde craftyly before men which befor God they bore in theyr hertis / They here / thou ſhalt not ſlee / do fornicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / 
<pb facs="tcp:5270:39"/>or ſtell / they do not drawe theyre ſword / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey do not myxe themſelues with harlottis they do not lay theyr handis an other mens godis. Al this is wel / but they brethe ſtriues with all theyr hertis / they burne in veneriall deſyrs / they ſpy the goodis of allmene with ſchoymiſche eyes / and dewouere all by couyt tuouſnes. Nowe they lackyd the chefyſte pownte of the lawe / Agaynſt thes Paulle<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrongely try / affirmynge the lawe to be ſpirituall / that is / which requiryth the hole mynde / the hole ſowle / and hollwyll obedien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / and whan we ſay this to be the ſum of the lawe we brynge no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we interpretacion / but folowe Chriſte the beſt interpreter of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we / which dyd adde nothynge to the lawe but only cleryt obſcuryd by the lys of phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys / and corrupte by theyr ſower dow.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> Lyke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yce as the vertue of his worde / the ſpryte of his mowthe doth nowe alſo reproue An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt and his ſecte which reyoyſſe onely in theyre workis / thynkynge themſelues more holy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> othere by caus they haue ſuch harde rules &amp; orders / ceremonys wous that no chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten man can ber or ſoffere. To whom was thes wordis ſpokyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e loue youre ennymys / do wel to them which hate you / pray for thez
<pb facs="tcp:5270:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>which perſecute you / that ye may be the chy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of the heuenly fathere / Who ſhalbe nowe the chyldren of the heuenly fathere? The Pope and hys angels / Monkis &amp; Cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nons / freyrs and herityke &amp;c. Then er we well at aes if the powle ſhorne marchantis ſhuld be only the ſons of God / if they ſhuld call God only theyr fathers? Therfor the word of God do proue them onely the ſons of the deuell / which do caſte a way ſo lightly the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moune youke of the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gode. But here theyre drowſy dreme / Owre lyfe were to herd for Chriſten men / As thowgh they culd make a thynge more herder then to loue God with all the hert / mend &amp; ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght / And aboue thys there is nothynge / that can be thowght ſpoke or done / which no man can performe &amp; fulfyll (as I ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore) in thys lyfe / Owre ymbecilite is nott abyll to performe the leſt yotte of the lawe / It is the Lord in whom we do vertue / He ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uet that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manunde / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund that he wyllyth / Chriſtians to be vnder the lawe of grace / is not of preſumpſion to walke with owt alawe / but to be ingryffyd in Chriſte by whos grace we be deliueryd from the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lediction of the lawe / and by whos ſpyght<note place="margin">The fyrſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te is her dere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall.</note>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roma.</hi> 9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">we fulfyll the lawe on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5270:40"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e haue the lawe wryttyn in owr hertis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herfor in all thyngis / lett vs reſpecte the ende of the lawe that is Ieſu Chriſt, which made vs of nawght / and loſte / reſtoryd vs agene to the heuenly fathere by pryſe of his precious blude / to the whych fathere
/ ſone / &amp; holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortere be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce honor &amp; glory / as it hath byn is &amp; ſhalbe for euer and euer.</p>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Euery planttacion which my heuenly fathere hath not planttyd / ſhalbe plucte vp by the rotte.</p>
                     <bibl>Ihon. 15.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Printyde at Baſyl by me Theophyll Emlos / vndere the ſygne of ſente Peters kay.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
